it is a matter of privilege to have a
miss us
gupta as a chief guest for convocation
badge
2019-21 please put your hands together
as i now invite our esteemed chief guest
to deliver the 33rd convocation address
thank you
um respected uh shimati jaishimotha
dr chatur vedi
dr dube dr verma
dr casey arora and professor dr
chattaraj
proud parents who are
probably listening to this live seeing
this wonderful function
and
this wonderful batch of 1921.
congratulations to all of you this is a
special day
you know it's a great honor for me to be
here
and
if i'm candid with you i'm
you know i'm facing what is known as
the imposter syndrome
if you if you research this what the
imposter system is syndrome does
is uh
it makes you wonder whether you deserve
to be here in the first place
when i look at some of the luminaries
who've come and addressed you in the
earlier chief guest functions as you've
guessed in these functions
they're real tough acts to follow
so i do hope i measure up
three months back in november
uh professor chataraj reached out to me
and
asked me if i would
do the honors
and i accepted it gladly
i thought that you know those three
months time to prepare for the speech
and i did want to prepare for the speech
you know it was important it was special
it was an honor
and exactly as all of you prepare for
your exams
or your special
assignments you want to work hard right
from the throughout the course i also
wanted to prepare for three months for
the speech
and then last week
a letter came from doctor chaturvedi
giving me the program and
asking me for the copy of the speech
you know that's when panic struck
just like you i hadn't prepared for the
exam
i had left it for the last minute
so i sat down last week thinking about
what to talk to you about
and then i realized it's an even bigger
problem
you know what do i share with
a bunch of smart intelligent very aware
very knowledgeable young people
for whom today knowledge is at their
fingertips you just take out your phone
and google
and what about wisdom the pearls of
wisdom that you expect
you know these days you get uh
every morning on your whatsapp univer
university pearls of wisdom right single
bit size memes
but there is an expectation you know
someone who is more than 50 gray hair
more than 30 years in corporate life
you expect to have some nuggets of
knowledge
some unique
wisdom but the problem is when you go
through life
you realize that
knowledge
has a funny picture
when you start out you know it's got a
shape of an inverted parabola so if you
have a
x-axis of age
and
the y-axis is your conviction about your
knowledge
you realize that it's an inverted
parabola
so some of you who remembered the shape
of the parabola you are you understand
what i'm trying to say
when you're very young
as a child
you know that you don't know much
and you're very keen to learn
and then as you go through your
schooling your college and you come to
the end of your
academic
you know phase of your career or life
you think you know everything because
you've reached the peak of your
knowledge
and then when you go through life you
read more you learn more you keep the
windows of your mind open
you realize that
there is so much more to learn what you
get to realize is the level of your
ignorance
so when i think about
those days when i was
like you and you know just out of
college
i thought i knew everything
when i joined the company that i joined
i thought
i know how to run this company better
than the ceo
i knew what the problems of the country
was and how to solve them
in fact
i'm sure all of you know
what the indian selectors should do in
terms of who to make the captain so that
india wins the world cup so all of you
know that right
but as i said life teaches you that
knowledge is a vast ocean and we are
just dipping our feet in that
ocean of knowledge
so what do i tell you
life also teaches you that
things are not black and white
you know there are perspectives there
are nuances
there is no correct one answer every
answer question has two different
answers any both could be correct
so life teaches you a lot
but then life is also full of stories
right
good stories bad stories
happy stories sad stories
some simple some profound
and these stories
give you those perspectives give you
those experiences
teach you lessons which
you can only learn by going through life
so i thought i'll share three of those
stories
that have taught me lessons
which i hope as you join your
professional life will help you some
time or the other
because there'll be some times where
you'll need those lessons
so my first story is set in 1970
i was a very young boy maybe four and
five years old this is actually one of
my first memories of my life
so we were growing up in this
middle class locality in calcutta
my parents love gardening
and my mother particularly loved love
for our flowers
and across the road there was this uh
house with a bigger garden beautiful
lawn
and in the garden they used to grow
these beautiful flowers dahlias christen
thomas roses
and in the winters you would go and play
in their in their lawn
now one day after our you know afternoon
games uh
two three of us i think three of us were
about our same age four five years old
kids
we saw these flowers and we felt that
these flowers are so beautiful they
should be at our homes why should they
be here
so we just went out and
plucked as many of these flowers as we
could
half bloom full bloom buds
and we just took them home
i thought my mother would
be very happy she loved flowers right
and she was like an usual indian mother
very loving very warm very caring
so i was looking forward to
a lot of shavashi you know maybe some
hugs
but boy was i wrong
i saw a different side of my father of
my mother
she gave me the worst firing worst
scolding of my life till that day
i didn't end there
she told me that you must take these
flowers go back to the neighbor
and say sorry
i was shattered i mean i said you know i
pleaded i requested but she was adamant
i had no choice
so i remember this is one of those
sinking feelings in your stomach in your
stomach you
you you feel small you feel terrible
and i was standing outside there this
neighbor's door ringing the bell waiting
for the door to open
hating every moment
and the door opens this lady comes out
and takes me in and i tell her what has
happened and i say sorry
so she listens to me and
just laughs
and then she uh speaks kindly with me
she gives me a glass of cold drink which
i happily have
who doesn't like cold drinks at that age
and that was the end of my punishment
so that incident taught me three lessons
in life
the first one was a management lesson on
a lighter vein
you know never take your consumer for
granted really understand what the
consumer wants i thought my mother loved
flowers i didn't realize that to her how
i got those flowers forever more
important than the flowers themselves
but they're two very important life
lessons
one was the importance of taking
responsibility for reactions
and the second even more important
lesson was that
when you make a mistake
be the first one to acknowledge to own
the mistake
that day if
our neighbor that lady had discovered
her broken garden before i went and told
her
she would have not been so charitable
she would not have been so kind she
would have been upset she would have
been angry she may have figured out who
had done it and come home and complain
the fact that i went and complained and
she discovered that through me as i was
apologizing took this thing
away to me that's been one of the
biggest lessons in life
and
through your career there will be times
when something under your watch will
go wrong something you'll mess up
somewhere
at that point in time
i would request i would hope that you
own up and you take responsibility
let me tell you one thing my experience
is that
when you take control when you take
responsibility
it is very very very liberating
it takes away anxiety it gives you a
sense of control over your own life you
don't worry about
what others have done to you you think
about what you could have done to
prevent something from going
wrong to me that was one important
lesson
of my life learned a very early age
and i hope when
something happens in your own lives in
your careers
you'll have that same courage same
conviction to own up
trust me it's the best way
my second story is more recent maybe
about nine ten years back
i was already in icc lombard
going around the country meeting agents
so in one of these meetings
there was about 40 50 agents uh you know
big important agents of that particular
city
and i was meeting them i was getting to
know them so it was like a typical town
hall
we were having very common conversations
about you know industry about growth
about
their business products commission
i was getting to know them i was asking
questions about their business they were
asking questions about our company and i
was explaining
and as we were going around the room
there was this one old agent who was
one of the oldest ones someone who
clearly commanded a lot of respect of
the
other agents he was maybe 65 70 years
old
and when his turn came
and i asked him about his business he
stood up and he started speaking
and as he did he taught me another huge
lesson in life
he stood up and he talked about his
business he said
his insurance company the the insurance
business agency business was set up by
his great grandfather in the british era
hundred years back
and it was business that had been
continued by his grandfather by his
father and by him
and then he
paused and he says he looked around the
room and he asked everyone do you know
why this is so why my family has been
doing this business why i still continue
to do this business that my
great grandfather set up
and he paused for effect
and then he said
because we do god's work
and he said that
with so much of conviction so much of
passion
that the room fell silent
it was one of those moments
you know one of those goosebumps moments
and then he explained he said you know
what we do is when things go bad for our
customers when they're down they have
ill health they have an accident
something has burned down that's when we
come and help them
get back to their feet
so he taught us a lesson in purpose you
know you all of you read management
books people talk about
organization purpose that man that day
taught me a lesson of purpose a lesson
of passion for one's work
now why am i telling you the story is it
to tell you that you should be
passionate about the work that you do or
follow your dreams you know follow your
heart that's
very cliche right that's
one of those whatsapp lessons that come
every day
no the reason why i'm telling you the
story is
for two reasons
one
if you realize why that man felt so
passionate about his work
was not because of self-interest
as you go through life and this is true
for all of us as we've gone through our
early days of career
you believe that your biggest joy
biggest motivation comes from the size
of your paycheck
your designation
your promotions every other day
and after some time in life you realize
that
true motivation through joy through
enjoyment of your work
comes if your motivation is comes from
something outside of yourself something
bigger than yourself
maybe setting up a great organization
maybe doing something which solves the
problem of society maybe helping
customers in distress
maybe helping your team your colleagues
achieve their true potential
that's the lesson that that old man
taught me that day
and the other lesson that i wanted to
share with you is that
you'll always be surprised to find
passionate people in surprising places
there is a view that you
can be passionate about only this job or
only that job
that is not so
in my career i start when i started and
from then on i've been a shop floor
engineer
i've been a credit analyst i've been a
project finance officer i've been a
startup incubator i've been an
international banker i've been a life
insurer i've been a right now i'm
running a general insurance company
at the start of my career i never never
never imagined that i would do all of
these things
you can't plan your career even if you
think that you can
and to me
each of those jobs have taught me a lot
they've been
very enjoyable there's been something
very engaging something very
enjoyable about every one of those jobs
and if at any point in time i had felt
that this role and by the way all these
jobs are not something that i deserved
some of them i did some of them were
given to me
so
each of these stages if i had felt that
i do not like this job
i like that other job
it is i who would have lost out
so the reason why i'm sharing this story
is to
request you and advise you and suggest
to you
that
there is something to learn something to
enjoy something to be passionate about
everything that you do
and that is the choice that you make
whether to like the work that you do
or hanker for something else
so as i said the story the the standard
meme says that
love the if you find the job that you
love you'll never work a single day
but i would say that not only
go for the job that you love but love
everything that you do
that will take you places
my third story is uh
not really a story
it's about the 30 years of experience in
icha group when i started it was just
around the time of financial
liberalization
business was simple low very low
competition credit spreads were
administered it was easy business it was
like rationing of the business and then
91 financial liberalization completely
disrupted the business model
and through those 30 years i've seen the
organization completely transformed go
you know kind of turn topsy turvy i've
seen days of heavy growth i've seen days
which are
full of crises where everything seems
hopeless
and i've been fortunate to see people of
some brilliant leaders in that period
some of my leaders business leaders were
doings of the industry
some of my peers who have set blazing
trails for themselves some of my juniors
were very talented and have become
industrial leaders themselves
and one thing that i've seen observing
the company and these individuals is
that
successful businesses that you see and
you applaud from outside
have all gone through very very
difficult times they've had
terrible struggles they've had very
serious crisis
and the true leaders are the ones that
deal with that crisis well they take it
in the stride
learn from it come out of it strong show
resilience
i was talking to uh dr vedi and you know
honestly what you guys have gone through
during the crisis of this pandemic
is
really something that has made you
resilient
so
at one level you may feel that you know
you missed out something but another
level i personally believe has made you
much stronger
so that's a big lesson that i've seen
that you know resilience is key because
life is not a bed of roses you have your
ups and downs
and the other lesson in those difficult
times is that
you need support systems and the best
support system that you have is here
around yourself
these two years you've spent time
together you've bonded you've studied
together you've been on with canteens
you've played you've made music you've
probably done drama gone to movies
you form strong bonds of friendships
don't let them go because these are
friends who will be around you when you
need them the most
so when anyone of your group needs any
help
please reach out and help them and if
you are
down
don't feel shy of reaching out
your batch will be your biggest support
group at least that's my experience
so these are the three stories that i
wanted to tell you
a story of
the lessons that i learned of them the
lessons of taking ownership
of true passion and of resilience
you know your batch is coming out you're
now done your academic work and you're
now coming into you know a professional
world
and there's a saying which says that may
you live in interesting times
it's supposed to be a curse but i think
it's a blessing who wants to live in
boring times particularly when you're
young and raring to go
and you're coming out a time the world
is very interesting because a huge
change happening geopolitics the power
of the world is shifting from the west
to east
technology technology is getting is
disrupting every business
huge global liquidity which is funding
that investment in technology and
consumer behavior changes that are
changing the way consumers expect you to
behave united companies
and these changes are very very positive
for india
as the power shifts from west to east
india is the right at the right place at
the right time
and you as you come into that
country
this country feels very different from
the country that we grew up in
it's full of energy it's full of
opportunity it's pregnant with
possibilities
and you have the opportunity of
making that happen and in the process
succeeding for yourselves
and i do hope that
as you come to this
economy and you shape well and you
succeed
i really wish you tremendous success
and i know that most of you will do
really well for yourself and be real
leaders but remember for every
successful and a powerful leader in this
country there are 100 people who need
your help and your support
so retain your kindness
retain your sense of empathy
retain your sense of responsibility for
your fellow fellow countrymen
batch of 1921 i again congratulate you
for
whatever you achieve today and i wish
you well i wish you all the success may
you achieve your true potential make
yourself your institute and your parents
proud
and as you succeed
stay human
stay humble
and be happy
thank you hello
mr how are you
fine fine ma'am thank you thank you it's
been an honor to be here with you
i've met you not in person but at least
on the screen i've met you
and your talk was so inspiring and you
know as you said it was not cliche
you give gave actual uh stories and
examples it made it so interesting
and uh not only are the can you hear me
yes of course i can hear you ma'am not
only are the students must be very
inspired but i myself am very inspired
you know
and i don't know
we have tea plantations
and uh i'm going to go into it again
with great forward with all the
advice that you have given all the
inspiration that you have been thank you
so much thank you thank you so much very
kind of human thank you
[Music]
you